What stands between Africa's current prostrate condition
ما الذي يقف بين وضع أفريقيا الواهن الحالي
and a future of prosperity and abundance for its long-suffering populations?
وبين مستقبل من الازدهار والوفرة لشعوبها التي عانت طويلًا؟
One word:
هو كلمة واحدة،
knowledge.
المعرفة.
If Africa is to become a continent that offers the best life for humans,
إذا أصبحت أفريقيا قارة تقدّم حياة أفضل لسكانها،
it must become a knowledge society
يجب أن تصبح مجتمع معرفة
immediately.
في الحال.
This is what I have called "Africa's knowledge imperative."
هذا ما أسميته "ضرورة انتشار المعرفة في أفريقيا."
Our universities must reduce emphasis on producing manpower
يجب أن تقلل جامعاتنا من تركيزها على إنتاج القوى العاملة
for running our civil society,
لإدارة مجتمعنا المدني
our economy
واقتصادنا
and our political institutions.
ومؤسساتنا السياسية.
They should be dedicated mainly to knowledge production.
يجب أن تكرس هدفها نحو إنتاج المعرفة
What sense is there in producing civil engineers
ما معني تخريج مهندسين مدنيين
who are not supported by soil scientists and geologists,
غير مدعومين بعلماء التربة والجيولوجيين،
who make it their business to create knowledge about our soil
الذين يعملون علي خلق المعرفة عن تربتنا
and our rocks?
وصخورنا؟
What use is there in producing lawyers
ما الفائدة من تخريج محامين
without juries who produce knowledge
بدون محلفين يعملون على صياغة المعرفة
of the underlying philosophical foundations of the legal system?
الخاصة بالأسس الفلسفية للنظام القانوني؟
We must seek knowledge.
علينا أن نسعى للمعرفة.
We must approach the matter of knowledge
يجب أن نعالج مسألة المعرفة
with a maniacal commitment,
بالتزام كبير،
without let or hindrance.
بدون تنازل أو تأخير.
Though we must seek knowledge to solve problems we know of,
يجب أن نسعى للمعرفة لكي نحل المشكلات التي نعلمها،
we must also seek knowledge
يجب أيضًا أن نسعى للمعرفة
when there is no problem in view --
حينما لا تكون هناك مشكلة واضحة،
especially when there is no problem in view.
خاصةً حينما لا تكون هناك مشكلة واضحة.
We must seek to know as much of what there is to know of all things,
يجب أن نسعى للمعرفة الممكنة عن كل شيء،
limited only by the insufficiency of our human nature,
ولا يمنعنا سوى عجز طبيعتنا البشرية،
and not only when the need arises.
وليس فقط عندما نحتاج لتطبيقها.
Those who do not seek knowledge when it is not needed
لأن الذين لا يسعون للمعرفة طالما أنهم لا يحتاجونها
will not have it when they must have it.
لن يمتلكوها عندما يجب عليهم ذلك.
The biggest crisis in Africa today is the crisis of knowledge:
مشكلة المعرفة هي أكبر مشاكل أفريقيا اليوم
how to produce it,
كيفية إنتاجها،
how to manage it,
كيفية إدارتها،
and how to deploy it effectively.
وكيفية نشرها بكفاءة.
For instance, Africa does not have a water crisis.
علي سبيل المثال، لا تعاني أفريقيا من أزمة مياه،
It has a knowledge crisis regarding its water,
لكن لديها أزمة معرفة بخصوص المياه،
where and what types it is,
أين وما هي أنواعها،
how it can be tapped and made available where and when needed to all and sundry.
كيف يمكن استغلالها وتوفيرها حيث ومتى يحتاجها الجميع بلا استثناء.
How does a continent that is home
كيف يمكن لقارة تعتبر مصدرًا
to some of the largest bodies of water in the world --
لبعض أعظم موارد المياه في العالم،
the Nile,
نهر النيل،
the Niger,
نهر النيجر،
the Congo,
نهر الكونغو،
the Zambezi
نهر الزامبيزي،
and the Orange Rivers --
وأنهار الأورنج،
be said to have a water crisis,
كيف يقال أن لديها أزمة مائية،
including in countries
حتي في الدول
where those rivers are?
التي تجري بها هذه الأنهار؟
And that is only surface water.
وهذه فقط المياه السطحية،
While we wrongly dissipate our energies fighting the wrong crises,
بينما نهدر طاقاتنا بالخطأ في محاربة الأزمات الخاطئة،
all those who invest in knowledge about us
كل هؤلاء الذين استثمروا في المعرفة عنا
are busy figuring out how to pipe water from Libya's aquifers
مشغولين باسكتشاف طريقة لضخ المياه الجوفية من (ليبيا)
to quench Europe's thirst.
لري عطش أوروبا.
Such is our knowledge of our water resources
هذه هي معرفتنا بمصادرنا المائية
that many of our countries have given up
التي تخلت عنها كثير من الدول
on making potable water a routine presence
في توفير المياه الصالحة للشرب بشكل عادي
in the lives of Africans,
في حياة الأفارقة،
rich or poor,
أغنياء وفقراء،
high and low,
للأشخاص المهمين والعاديين،
rural and urban.
من الريف أو المدن.
We eagerly accept what the merchants of misery
لقد تقبلنا بلهفة ما أخبرنا به تجار التعاسة
and the global African Studies safari professoriat
والدراسات الاستقصائية العالمية عن أفريقيا
and their aid-addled,
بمساعداتهم الفاسدة،
autonomy-fearing African minions
وخوفهم من توابع الاستقلال الذاتي
in government, universities and civil society
في الحكومة والجامعات والمجتمع المدني
tell us regarding how nature has been to stinting towards Africa
عن أن الطبيعة لم تكن كريمة مع أفريقيا
when it comes to the distribution of water resources in the world.
عند توزيع مصادر المياه في العالم.
We are content to run our cities and rural dwellings alike
نحن علي استعداد لإدارة مدننا ومنازلنا الريفية علي السواء
on boreholes.
بمياه الآبار.
How does one run metropolises on boreholes and wells?
كيف يمكن لأحد أن يدير المدن بمياه الآبار؟
Does Africa have a food crisis?
هل تعاني أفريقيا من أزمة غذاء؟
Again, the answer is no.
مرة أخرى، الإجابة لا.
It is yet another knowledge crisis regarding Africa's agricultural resources,
تعد مع ذلك أزمة معرفة أخرى فيما يتعلق بمصادر أفريقيا الزراعية،
what and where they are,
ما هي وأين توجد،
and how they can be best managed to make Africans live more lives
وكيف يمكن إدارتها ليعيش الأفارقة بشكل أفضل
that are worth living.
الحياة التي يستحقونها.
Otherwise, how does one explain the fact
بطريقة أخرى، كيف يمكن للمرء شرح واقع
that geography puts the source of the River Nile in Ethiopia,
أن الجغرافيا تضع منابع نهر النيل في أثيوبيا،
and its people cannot have water for their lives?
ولا يجد الناس هناك المياه لأجل معيشتهم؟
And the same geography puts California in the desert,
وتضع نفس الجغرافيا كاليفورنيا في الصحراء،
but it is a breadbasket.
لكنها تعتبر سلة غذاء.
The difference, obviously, is not geography.
الفرق بوضوح ليس في الجغرافيا.
It is knowledge.
إنها المعرفة.
Colorado's aquifers
مستودعات المياه الجوفية في (كولورادو)
grow California's pistachios.
تروي شجر الفستق في كاليفورنيا.
Why can't Libya's aquifers
لماذا لاتروي المياه الجوفية في ليبيا
grow sorghum in northern Nigeria?
الذرة البيضاء في شمال نيجيريا؟
Why does Nigeria not aspire
لماذا لا تطمح نيجيريا
to feed the world,
إلى توفير الغذاء للعالم،
not just itself?
ليس لنفسها فقط؟
If Africa's land is so poor, as we are often told,
إذا كانت أراضي أفريقيا فقيرة كما يخبرونا
why are outsiders,
لماذا يشتري الغرباء
from the United Arab Emirates all the way to South Korea,
ابتداءً من الإمارات العربية المتحدة إلي كوريا الجنوبية
buying up vast acreages of our land,
مساحات شاسعة من أراضينا،
to grow food, no less,
لزراعة الغذاء فقط،
to feed their people
وإطعام شعوبهم
in lands that are truly more geographically stinting?
في الأراضي التي هي حقًا فقيرة جغرافيًا؟
The new landowners are not planning to import new topsoil
لا يخطط الملاك الجدد لاستيراد طبقات عليا
to make their African acquisitions more arable.
لزيادة خصوبة الأراضي التي حصلوا عليها.
Again, a singular instance of knowledge deficiency.
مرة أخرى، هذا مثال مميز علي قصور المعرفة.
In the 19th century,
في القرن التاسع عشر،
our predecessors,
قام أسلافنا
just years removed from the ravages of slavery and the slave trade,
بعد سنوات قليلة من التخلص من الرق وتجارة الرقيق،
were exploring the Niger and Congo Rivers
باسكتشاف نهري النيجر والكونغو
with a view to turning Africa's resources to the advantage of its people
بهدف استخدام مصادر أفريقيا لمصلحة شعوبها
and to the rest of humanity,
وللبشرية جمعاء،
and their 20th-century successors were dreaming of harnessing
وكان يحلم خلفاؤهم في القرن العشرين
the powers of the River Congo
بتسخير قوى نهر الكونغو
to light up the whole continent.
لإضاءة القارة بأكملها.
Now only buccaneer capitalists from Europe
الآن فقط القراصنة من الرأسماليين من أوروبا
are scheming of doing the same,
يخططون لفعل الشيء نفسه،
but for exports to Europe and South Africa.
لكن بحق صادرات أوروبا وجنوب أفريقيا.
And they are even suggesting
لدرجة أنهم يقترحون
that Congolese may not benefit from this scheme,
أنه قد لا يستفيد الكونغوليون من هذا المخطط،
because, according to them, Congolese communities are too small
لأن بالنسبة لهم المجتمعات في الكونغو صغيرة للغاية
to make providing them with electricity
حتى يمثل توفير الكهرباء لهم
a viable concern.
شاغلًا مهمًا.
The solution?
ما الحل؟
Africa must become a knowledge society,
يجب أن تصبح أفريقيا مجتمعًا معرفيًا،
a defining characteristic of the modern age.
يتمتع بخصائص العصر الحديث.
We neither are, nor are we on the path to becoming,
نحن لسنا مجتمعًا معرفيًا أو حتى على الطريق لنصبح
a knowledge society.
مجتمع معرفيًا.
Things have not always been this way
الأمور لم تكن دومًا كذلك
when it comes to knowledge production and Africa.
حينما نتحدث عن إنتاج المعرفة وأفريقيا.
In antiquity, the world went to Africa for intellectual enrichment.
في العصور القديمة اتجه العالم إلي أفريقيا من أجل الإثراء الفكري.
There were celebrated centers of learning,
كانت هناك مراكز تعليم شهيرة
attracting questers from all parts of the then-known world,
تجذب الباحثين من جميع أجزاء العالم المعروف حينها،
seeking knowledge about that world.
في سعيهم لمعرفة ذلك العالم.
What happened then has implications for our present.
ما حدث حينها له نتائجه على حاضرنا.
For example,
على سبيل المثال،
how Roman Africa managed the relationship between settlers and natives
كيفية إدارة الرومان للعلاقة بين المستوطنين والسكان الأصليين
between the second and fourth centuries of our era
بين القرن الثاني والرابع من تاريخنا
might have something to teach us when it comes to confronting
ربما يعلمنا ذلك شيئًا عن مواجهة
not-too-dissimilar problems at the present time.
مشكلات لا تختلف كثيرًا عن الوقت الحالي.
But how many classics departments do we have in our universities?
لكن كم عدد أقسام دراسة الأدب القديم في جامعاتنا؟
Because we do not invest in knowledge,
لأننا لا نستثمر في المعرفة،
people come to Africa now
يأتي الناس إلي أفريقيا اليوم
not as a place of intellectual enrichment,
ليس كمكان للإثراء الفكري،
but as a place where they sate their thirst for exotica.
ولكن كمكان يروي عطشهم للغرابة.
Yet for the last half-millennium,
في النصف الأخير من الألفية،
Africa has been hemorrhaging and exporting knowledge
أنتجت أفريقيا المعرفة بغزارة وصدرتها
to the rest of the world.
لبقية العالم.
Regardless of the popular description of it as a trade in bodies,
بغض النظر عن وصفها الشهير بالمتاجرة في البشر،
the European trans-Atlantic slave trade and slavery
كان الرق وتجارة الرقيق في أوروبا عبر المحيط الأطلسي
was one of the most radical and longest programs
يمثل واحدًا من أكثر البرامج عنصرية وأطولها
of African brains export in history.
في تصدير العقول الأفريقية في التاريخ.
American slave owners may have pretended that Africans were mere brutes,
ربما يدعي مُلّاك العبيد الأمريكيين أن الأفارقة كانوا مجرد متوحشين،
beasts of burden,
وحوش لحمل الأشياء،
almost as inert and dumb as other farm implements
تشبه باقي الأدوات الزراعية الأخرى في الخمول والصمت
they classified them with in their ledgers.
لقد صنفوهم في دفاترهم.
And that's what they did.
وهذا ما فعلوه.
The enslaved Africans, on the other hand,
في الناحية الأخرى، الأفارقة المستعبدون
knew their were embodiments of knowledge.
عرفوا أنهم تجسيدات للمعرفة.
They were smiths, they were poets,
كانوا حدادين، كانوا شعراء،
they were political counselors, they were princes and princesses,
كانوا مستشارين سياسيين، كانوا أمراء وأميرات،
they were mythologists, they were herbologists,
كانوا كتاب ميثولوجيا وخبراء علاج بالأعشاب،
they were chefs.
كانوا طهاة.
The list is endless.
القائمة لا تنتهي.
They, to take a single example,
لأعطيكم مثالًا واحدًا،
brought the knowledge of rice cultivation
لقد جلبوا طريقة زراعة الأرز
to the American South.
إلى جنوب أمريكا.
They created some of the most original civilizational elements
لقد أبدعوا في بعض مقوّمات الحضارة الأصيلة
for which the United States is now celebrated.
التي تفتخر بها الولايات المتحدة اليوم.
They deployed their knowledge, for the most part,
ونشروا معارفهم لأقصى درجة،
without compensation.
بدون أخذ أي تعويض.
For the last half-millennium, beginning with the slave trade,
طوال النصف الأخير من الألفية، بداية من تجارة الرقيق
Africa has been exporting brains
تصدّر أفريقيا العقول
while simultaneously breaking the chains of knowledge transmission
بينما تكسر قيود نقل المعرفة في آنٍ واحد
on the continent itself,
إلى القارة نفسها،
with dire consequences for the systems of knowledge production in Africa.
بما له من عواقب وخيمة على أنظمة إنتاج المعرفة في أفريقيا.
Successive generations are cut off from the intellectual production
انقطع اتصال الأجيال المتعاقبة عن الإنتاج الفكري
of their predecessors.
الخاص بأسلافهم.
We keep producing for external markets
نظل ننتج لصالح الأسواق الخارجية
while beggaring our own internal needs.
بينما نفتقر إلى احتياجاتنا الداخلية.
At present,
في الوقت الحالي،
much of the best knowledge about Africa
الكثير من أفضل المعارف عن أفريقيا
is neither produced nor housed there,
لم يُنتج في أفريقيا أو يُستوطن بها،
even when it is produced by Africans.
حتى تلك التي أنتجها الأفارقة.
Because we are dominated by immediate needs
لأننا محكومون باحتياجات عاجلة
and relevant solutions when it comes to what we should know,
والحل الأقرب عندما يتعلق الأمر بما يجب أن نعلمه،
we are happy to hand over to others
نسعد بأن نسلّم للآخرين
the responsibility to produce knowledge,
مسؤولية إنتاج المعرفة
including knowledge about, of and for us,
حتى المعرفة عنا ولأجلنا،
and to do so far away from us.
وينتجوها بعيدًا عن متناولنا.
We are ever eager to consume knowledge
نحن متحمسون أكثر من ذي قبل لاستهلاك المعرفة.
and have but a mere portion of it
لقد أنتجنا جزءًا منها
without any anxiety about ownership and location.
دون أن نقلق على ملكيتها أو موقعها.
African universities are now all too content
واطمأنت الجامعات الأفريقية كثيرًا
to have e-connections with libraries elsewhere,
إلى التواصل الإلكتروني مع المكتبات في أماكن أخرى،
having given up ambitions on building libraries
وتخلت عن طموحها لبناء المكتبات
to which the world would come for intellectual edification.
التي يحتاج إليها العالم للتنوير الفكري.
Control over who decides what should be stocked on our shelves
التحكم في من سيقرر نوعية الكتب التي يجب أن توضع على الرفوف
and how access to collections should be determined
وكيفية تحديد طريقة الوصول إلي مختارات الكتب
are made to rest on our trust in our partners' good faith
يعتمد علي الثقة في النية الحسنة لشركائنا
that they will not abandon us down the road.
وأنهم لن يتخلوا عنا في منتصف الطريق.
This must change.
يجب أن يتغير هذا.
Africa must become a place of knowledge again.
يجب أن تصبح أفريقيا مكانًا للمعرفة مجددًا.
Knowledge production actually expands the economy.
في الواقع إنتاج المعرفة يحسن الاقتصاد.
Take archaeological digs, for instance,
على سبيل المثال، الحفريات الأثرية،
and their impact on tourism.
وتأثيرها على السياحة.
Our desires to unearth our antiquity,
رغبتنا في الكشف عن عصورنا القديمة
especially those remote times of which we have no written records,
خاصةً الأزمنة البعيدة التي ليس لها سجلات مكتوبة
requires investment in archaeology and related disciplines,
تتطلب الاستثمار في علم الآثار والتخصصات،
e.g., paleoanthropology.
مثل علم أصول البشر.
Yet, although it is our past we seek to know,
على الرغم من أننا نسعى للتعرف علي ماضينا
by sheer serendipity,
بمحض الصدفة،
archaeology may shed light on the global human experience
قد يسلط علم الآثار الضوء على تجربة الإنسان العالمية
and yield economic payoffs
ويحقق فوائد اقتصادية
that were no part of the original reasons for digging.
التي لم تكن جزءًا من أسباب البحث الأصلية.
We must find a way to make knowledge and its production sexy and rewarding;
يجب أن نجد طريقة لجعل المعرفة وإنتاجها أمرًا مثيرًا ومجزيًا.
rewarding, not in the crass sense of moneymaking
ليست مجزية بمنطق صناعة الأموال
but in terms of making it worthwhile to indulge in the pursuit of knowledge,
لكن بمنطق استحقاق المعرفة للسعي في إنتاجها،
support the existence
ودعم وجود
of knowledge-producing groups and intellectuals,
مجموعات إنتاج المعرفة والمفكرين،
ensuring that the continent
والتأكيد على أن تصبح القارة
becomes the immediate locus of knowledge production,
موقعًا مباشرًا لإنتاج المعرفة،
distribution and consumption,
وتوزيعها واستهلاكها.
and that instead of having its depositories
وذلك بدلًا من امتلاك مخازنها
beyond Africa's boundaries,
خارج حدود أفريقيا،
people once more come from the rest of the world,
جاء الناس قديمًا من جميع أنحاء العالم،
even if in virtual space, to learn from us.
حتى لو كانوا في فضاءٍ افتراضي، جاءوا ليتعلموا منا.
All this we do as custodians on behalf of common humanity.
وكل هذا فعلناه بوصفنا أمناء على مصالح الإنسانية المشتركة.
Creating a knowledge society in Africa,
إيجاد مجتمع معرفي في أفريقيا،
for me, would be one way to celebrate and simultaneously enhance diversity
بالنسبة لي، سيكون طريقة للاحتفال ولتعزيز التنوع في آنٍ واحد
by infinitely enriching it with material and additional artifacts --
عن طريق إثرائه بلا حدود بتوفير المواد الفنية والآثار الأخرى،
artifacts that we furnish
الآثار التي نوفرها
by our strivings
من خلال سعينا
in the knowledge field.
في مجال المعرفة.
Thank you very much.
شكرًا جزيلًا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)